<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter id="NT4Migration">
<chapterinfo>
	&author.jht;
	<pubdate>April 3, 2003</pubdate>
	<author>&person.sgw;<contrib>German Translation</contrib></author>
</chapterinfo>

<title>Migration von einem NT4-PDC auf einen Samba-3-PDC</title>

<para>
Dies ist eine grobe Anleitung, um jenen zu helfen, die von NT4-basierter Domänen-Verwaltung
auf Samba-3-basierte Domänen-Verwaltung migrieren wollen.
</para>

<sect1>
<title>Planung und Beginn</title>

<para>
In der IT-Welt gibt es den Satz, der besagt, daß alle Probleme infolge schlechter Planung entstehen.
Der Folgesatz dazu ist, daß nicht alle Probleme vorweggenommen und eingeplant werden können.
Jedoch wird gute Planung die meisten "Show-Stopper"-Situationen vorwegnehmen können.
</para>

<para>
Diejenigen, die von NT4-basierter Domänen-Verwaltung auf Samba-3-basierte 
Domänen-Verwaltung migrieren wollen, tun gut daran, einen detaillierten Migrations-Plan zu
entwickeln. Dazu gibt es in diesem Dokument einige Hinweise.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Zielsetzungen</title>

<para>
Die hauptsächliche Zielsetzung für die meisten Organisationen wird es sein, die Migration
von NT4- auf Samba-3-Domänen-Verwaltung so reibungslos wie möglich zu gestalten. Eine der
Herausforderungen, denen Sie in Ihrem Migrations-Prozeß begegnen werden, könnte sein, daß
Sie das Management davon überzeugen müssen, daß die neue Umgebung bestehen bleiben sollte.
Viele, die Open-Source-Technologie in Unternehmen eingebracht haben, haben es erlebt,
beim ersten Anzeichen von Problemen unter Druck gesetzt zu werden, 
zu Microsoft-basierten Lösungen zurückzukehren.
</para>

<para>
Bevor Sie eine Migration auf ein Samba-3-kontrolliertes Netz anstreben, unternehmen Sie
jegliche Anstrengung, um dafür Unterstützung von allen Seiten zu erhalten.
Vergewissern Sie sich, genau zu wissen, <emphasis>warum</emphasis> diese Veränderung
wichtig für diese Organisation ist. Mögliche Motivationen zur Veränderung beinhalten:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Das Verbessern des Netzwerk-Managements.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Das Erreichen besserer Funktionalität auf Benutzer-Ebene.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Das Reduzieren der Kosten für das Betreiben des Netzwerks.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Das Reduzieren der Kosten durch den Wegfall des MS-NT4-Supports.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Das Vermeiden der Auswirkungen der MS Lizenz 6.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Das Verringern der Abhängigkeiten von Microsoft.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Sorgen Sie dafür, daß jeder weiß, daß Samba-3 NICHT MS Windows NT4 ist. Samba-3 bietet eine
alternative Lösung, die sich einerseits von MS Windows NT4 unterscheidet, und andererseits
ihm gegenüber Vorteile bietet. Erreichen Sie, daß man erkennt, daß Samba-3 viele der Features
fehlen, die Microsoft als Schlüsselwerte in der Migration von MS Windows NT4 auf MS Windows 2000,
und darüber hinaus, beworben hat (mit oder ohne Active Directory-Dienste).
</para>

<para>
Welche Features kann Samba-3 nicht bieten?
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Active Directory Server.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Gruppen-Richtlinien-Objekte (im Active Directory).</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Maschinen-Richtlinien-Objekte.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Anmelde-Skripts im Active Directory.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Software-Anwendungs- und Zugriffs-Kontrolle im Active Directory.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Die Features, die Samba-3 anbietet, und die von zwingendem Interesse für Ihre Installation
sein können, sind:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>Geringere Kosten (Total Cost of Ownership, TCO).</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Globale Verfügbarkeit des Supports, ohne Verpflichtungen.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Dynamische SMB-Server (mehrere SMB/CIFS-Server per UNIX/Linux-System).</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Anlegen von on-the-fly-Anmelde-Skripts.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Anlegen von on-the-fly-Richtlinien-Dateien.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Höhere Stabilität, Verläßlichkeit, Performance und Verfügbarkeit.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Administration über eine ssh-Verbindung.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Flexible Wahl der Back-End Authentifizierungs-Technologie (tdbsam, ldapsam, mysqlsam).</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Mögliche Implementation einer vollen Single-Sign-On-Architektur.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>Die mögliche Verteilung von Authentifizierungs-Systemen zur Minimierung des Bandbreiten-Bedarfs.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Bedenken Sie vor der Migration eines Netzwerks von MS Windows NT4 auf Samba-3 alle notwendigen Faktoren.
Die Benutzer sollten über die Änderungen, die Sie bemerken könnten, informiert werden, sodaß die
Umstellung eine willkommene ist, und nicht ein Hindernis, das sie von ihrer Arbeit abhält.
Folgende Faktoren tragen zur Gewährleistung einer erfolgreichen Migration bei:
</para>

<sect3>
<title>Domänen-Entwurf</title>

<para>
Samba-3 kann als Domänen-Controller, als Backup-Domänen-Controller (vielleicht am besten als sekundärer
Controller bezeichnet), als Domänen-Mitglieds-Server, oder als Stand-Alone-Server konfiguriert werden.
Der Windows-Netzwerk-Domänen-Sicherheits-Kontext sollte dimensioniert und geprüft werden, und das
vor der Migration. Besondere Aufmerksamkeit sollte auf die Plazierung des PDCs und der BDCs gelegt werden.
Ein Unterschied zwischen Samba-3 und Microsoft-Technologie ist, daß man, wenn man sich für das
LDAP-Authentifizierungs-Backend entscheidet, die selbe Datenbank für mehrere verschiedene Domänen
benutzen kann. In einer komplexen Organisation kann es eine einzelne LDAP-Datenbank geben, welche
selbst verteilt werden kann (durch Verwendung eines Master- und mehrerer Slave-LDAP-Server), und die
mehrere Domänen bedienen kann.
</para>

<para>
Aus der Perspektive des Designs sollte die Anzahl der Benutzer pro Server, ebenso wie die Anzahl
der Server pro Domäne, unter Berücksichtigung der Server-Kapazitäten und Netzwerk-Bandbreiten
festgelegt werden.
</para>

<para>
Ein physisches Netzwerk-Segment kann mehrere Domänen beinhalten. Jede kann wiederum mehrere 
Netzwerk-Segmente umfassen. Wo Domänen geroutete Netzwerk-Segmente umfassen, bedenken und testen
Sie die Auswirkungen auf die Performance, die der Entwurf und das Design des Netzwerks haben können.
Ein zentral plazierter Domänen-Controller, der mehrere geroutete Netzwerk-Segmente bedienen soll, kann
ernsthafte Performance-Probleme verursachen. Prüfen Sie die Antwortzeiten (ping-Zeiten) zwischen
dem entfernten Segment und dem PDC. Sind diese lang (> 100 ms), plazieren Sie einen BDC im entfernten
Segment, um als lokaler Authentifikations- und Zugriffs-Kontroll-Server zu arbeiten.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Server Share and Directory Layout</title>

<para>
There are cardinal rules to effective network design that cannot be broken with impunity.
The most important rule: Simplicity is king in every well-controlled network. Every part of
the infrastructure must be managed; the more complex it is, the greater will be the demand
of keeping systems secure and functional.
</para>

<para>
Keep in mind the nature of how data must be shared. Physical disk space layout should be considered
carefully. Some data must be backed up. The simpler the disk layout the easier it will be to
keep track of backup needs. Identify what backup media will meet your needs; consider backup to tape,
CD-ROM or (DVD-ROM), or other offline storage medium. Plan and implement for minimum
maintenance. Leave nothing to chance in your design; above all, do not leave backups to chance:
Backup, test, and validate every backup, create a disaster recovery plan and prove that it works.
</para>

<para>
Users should be grouped according to data access control needs. File and directory access 
is best controlled via group permissions and the use of the <quote>sticky bit</quote> on group controlled
directories may substantially avoid file access complaints from Samba share users.
</para>

<para>
Inexperienced  network administrators often attempt elaborate techniques to set access
controls on files, directories, shares, as well as in share definitions.
Keep your design and implementation simple and document your design extensively. Have others
audit your documentation. Do not create a complex mess that your successor will not understand.
Remember, job security through complex design and implementation may cause loss of operations
and downtime to users as the new administrator learns to untangle your knots. Keep access
controls simple and effective and make sure that users will never be interrupted by obtuse
complexity.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Logon Scripts</title>

<para>
Logon scripts can help to ensure that all users gain the share and printer connections they need.
</para>

<para>
Logon scripts can be created on-the-fly so all commands executed are specific to the
rights and privileges granted to the user. The preferred controls should be affected through
group membership so group information can be used to create a custom logon script using
the <smbconfoption><name>root preexec</name></smbconfoption> parameters to the <smbconfsection>NETLOGON</smbconfsection> share.
</para>

<para>
Some sites prefer to use a tool such as <command>kixstart</command> to establish a controlled
user environment. In any case, you may wish to do a Google search for logon script process controls.
In particular, you may wish to explore the use of the Microsoft KnowledgeBase article KB189105 that
deals with how to add printers without user intervention via the logon script process.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Profile Migration/Creation</title>

<para>
User and Group Profiles may be migrated using the tools described in the section titled Desktop Profile
Management.
</para>


<para>
<indexterm><primary>SID</primary></indexterm>
Profiles may also be managed using the Samba-3 tool <command>profiles</command>. This tool allows
the MS Windows NT-style security identifiers (SIDs) that are stored inside the profile <filename>NTuser.DAT</filename> file
to be changed to the SID of the Samba-3 domain.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>User and Group Accounts</title>

<para>
It is possible to migrate all account settings from an MS Windows NT4 domain to Samba-3. Before
attempting to migrate user and group accounts, it is STRONGLY advised to create in Samba-3 the
groups that are present on the MS Windows NT4 domain <emphasis>AND</emphasis> to map them to
suitable UNIX/Linux groups. By following this simple advice, all user and group attributes
should migrate painlessly.
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Steps in Migration Process</title>

<para>
The approximate migration process is described below.
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>
You have an NT4 PDC that has the users, groups, policies and profiles to be migrated.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Samba-3 set up as a DC with netlogon share, profile share, and so on. Configure the &smb.conf; file
to fucntion as a BDC, i.e., <parameter>domain master = No</parameter>.
</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<procedure><title>The Account Migration Process</title>
	<step><para>
<indexterm><primary>pdbedit</primary></indexterm>
			Create a BDC account in the old NT4 domain for the Samba server using NT Server Manager.</para>
		<substeps><step><para>Samba must not be running.</para></step></substeps></step>


	<step><para>
<indexterm><primary>net</primary><secondary>rpc</secondary></indexterm>
			<userinput>net rpc join -S <replaceable>NT4PDC</replaceable> -w <replaceable>DOMNAME</replaceable> -U Administrator%<replaceable>passwd</replaceable></userinput></para></step>

	<step><para><userinput>net rpc vampire -S <replaceable>NT4PDC</replaceable> -U administrator%<replaceable>passwd</replaceable></userinput></para></step>

	<step><para><userinput>pdbedit -L</userinput></para>
		<substeps><step><para>Note &smbmdash; did the users migrate?</para></step></substeps>
	</step>


	<step><para>
<indexterm><primary>net</primary><secondary>groupmap</secondary></indexterm>
<indexterm><primary>initGroups.sh</primary></indexterm>
	Now assign each of the UNIX groups to NT groups:
	(It may be useful to copy this text to a script called <filename>initGroups.sh</filename>)
	<programlisting>
#!/bin/bash
#### Keep this as a shell script for future re-use
			
# First assign well known domain global groups
net groupmap modify ntgroup="Domain Admins" unixgroup=root   rid=512
net groupmap modify ntgroup="Domain Users"  unixgroup=users  rid=513
net groupmap modify ntgroup="Domain Guests" unixgroup=nobody rid=514

# Now for our added domain global groups
net groupmap add ntgroup="Designers" unixgroup=designers type=d rid=3200
net groupmap add ntgroup="Engineers" unixgroup=engineers type=d rid=3210
net groupmap add ntgroup="QA Team"   unixgroup=qateam    type=d rid=3220
</programlisting>
	</para></step>

	<step><para><userinput>net groupmap list</userinput></para>
		<substeps><step><para>Check that all groups are recognized.</para></step></substeps>
	</step>
</procedure>

<para>
Migrate all the profiles, then migrate all policy files.
</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Migration Options</title>

<para>
Sites that wish to migrate from MS Windows NT4 Domain Control to a Samba-based solution
generally fit into three basic categories. <link linkend="majtypes"/> shows the possibilities.
</para>

<table frame="all" id="majtypes"><title>The Three Major Site Types</title>
<tgroup cols="2">
	<colspec align="left"/>
	<colspec align="justify" colspec="1*"/>
	<thead>
	<row><entry>Number of Users</entry><entry>Description</entry></row>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	<row><entry>&lt; 50</entry><entry><para>Want simple conversion with no pain.</para></entry></row>
	<row><entry>50 - 250</entry><entry><para>Want new features, can manage some in-house complexity.</para></entry></row>
	<row><entry>&gt; 250</entry><entry><para>Solution/Implementation must scale well, complex needs. Cross-departmental decision process. Local expertise in most areas.</para></entry></row>
	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>

<sect2>
<title>Planning for Success</title>

<para>
There are three basic choices for sites that intend to migrate from MS Windows NT4
to Samba-3:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	Simple conversion (total replacement).
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Upgraded conversion (could be one of integration).
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Complete redesign (completely new solution).
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Minimize down-stream problems by:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
	Taking sufficient time.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Avoiding Panic.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Testing all assumptions.
	</para></listitem>

	<listitem><para>
	Testing the full roll-out program, including workstation deployment.
	</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para><link linkend="natconchoices"/> lists the conversion choices given the type of migration
being contemplated.
</para>

<table frame="all" id="natconchoices"><title>Nature of the Conversion Choices</title>
<tgroup cols="3">
	<colspec align="justify" colwidth="1*"/>
	<colspec align="justify" colwidth="1*"/>
	<colspec align="justify" colwidth="1*"/>
	<thead>
	<row><entry>Simple</entry><entry>Upgraded</entry><entry>Redesign</entry></row>
	</thead>
	<tbody>
	<row>
	<entry><para>Make use of minimal OS specific features.</para></entry>
	<entry><para>Translate NT4 features to new host OS features.</para></entry>
	<entry><para>Decide:</para></entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	<entry><para>Move all accounts from NT4 into Samba-3</para></entry>
	<entry><para>Copy and improve</para></entry>
	<entry><para>Authentication regime (database location and access)</para></entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	<entry><para>Make least number of operational changes</para></entry>
	<entry><para>Make progressive improvements</para></entry>
	<entry><para>Desktop management methods</para></entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	<entry><para>Take least amount of time to migrate</para></entry>
	<entry><para>Minimize user impact</para></entry>
	<entry><para>Better control of Desktops/Users</para></entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	<entry><para>Live versus isolated conversion</para></entry>
	<entry><para>Maximize functionality</para></entry>
	<entry><para>Identify Needs for: <emphasis>Manageability, Scalability, Security, Availability</emphasis></para></entry>
	</row>
	<row>
	<entry><para>Integrate Samba-3 then migrate while users are active, then change of control (swap out)</para></entry>
	<entry><para>Take advantage of lower maintenance opportunity</para></entry>
	<entry><para></para></entry>
	</row>
	</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Samba-3 Implementation Choices</title>

<variablelist>
	<varlistentry><term>Authentication Database/Backend</term><listitem>
		<para>
		Samba-3 can use an external authentication backend:
		</para>

		<para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem><para>Winbind (external Samba or NT4/200x server).</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>External server could use Active Directory or NT4 Domain.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Can use pam_mkhomedir.so to auto-create home dirs.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>
					Samba-3 can use a local authentication backend: <parameter>smbpasswd, tdbsam, ldapsam, mysqlsam</parameter></para></listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</listitem></varlistentry>

        <varlistentry><term>Access Control Points</term><listitem>
		<para>
		Samba permits Access Control Points to be set:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
                        <listitem><para>On the share itself &smbmdash; using Share ACLs.</para></listitem>
                        <listitem><para>On the file system &smbmdash; using UNIX permissions on files and directories.</para>
				<para>Note: Can enable Posix ACLs in file system also.</para></listitem>
                        <listitem><para>Through Samba share parameters &smbmdash; not recommended except as last resort.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry><term>Policies (migrate or create new ones)</term><listitem>
		<para>
		Exercise great caution when affecting registry changes, use the right tool and be aware
		that changes made through NT4-style <filename>NTConfig.POL</filename> files can leave
		permanent changes.
		</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem><para>Using Group Policy Editor (NT4).</para></listitem>
                        <listitem><para>Watch out for Tattoo effect.</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry><term>User and Group Profiles</term><listitem>
                <para>
		Platform-specific so use platform tool to change from a Local to a Roaming profile.
		Can use new profiles tool to change SIDs (<filename>NTUser.DAT</filename>).
		</para>
                </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry><term>Logon Scripts</term><listitem>
                <para>
		Know how they work.
		</para>
                </listitem>
        </varlistentry>


        <varlistentry><term>User and Group Mapping to UNIX/Linux</term><listitem>
		<para>
<indexterm><primary>pdbedit</primary></indexterm>
		User and Group mapping code is new. Many problems have been experienced as network administrators
		who are familiar with Samba-2.2.x migrate to Samba-3. Carefully study the chapters that document
		the new password backend behavior and the new group mapping functionality.
		</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem><para>The <parameter>username map</parameter> facility may be needed.</para></listitem>
                        <listitem><para>Use <command>net groupmap</command> to connect NT4 groups to UNIX groups.</para></listitem>
                        <listitem><para>Use <command>pdbedit</command> to set/change user configuration.</para>

				<para>
				When migrating to LDAP backend, it may be easier to dump the initial
				LDAP database to LDIF, edit, then reload into LDAP.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry><term>OS Specific Scripts/Programs may be Needed</term><listitem>
		<para>
		Every operating system has its peculiarities. These are the result of engineering decisions
		that were based on the experience of the designer, and may have side-effects that were not
		anticipated. Limitations that may bite the Windows network administrator include:
		</para>
                <itemizedlist>
                        <listitem><para>Add/Delete Users: Note OS limits on size of name
				(Linux 8 chars) NT4 up to 254 chars.</para></listitem>
                        <listitem><para>Add/Delete Machines: Applied only to Domain Members
				(Note: machine names may be limited to 16 characters).</para></listitem>
                        <listitem><para>Use <command>net groupmap</command> to connect NT4 groups to UNIX groups.</para></listitem>
                        <listitem><para>Add/Delete Groups: Note OS limits on size and nature.
				Linux limit is 16 char, no spaces and no upper case chars (<command>groupadd</command>).</para></listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
                </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry><term>Migration Tools</term><listitem>
                <para>
<indexterm><primary>pdbedit</primary></indexterm>
		Domain Control (NT4 Style) Profiles, Policies, Access Controls, Security
		<itemizedlist>
                        <listitem><para>Samba: <command>net, rpcclient, smbpasswd, pdbedit, profiles.</command></para></listitem>
                        <listitem><para>Windows: <command>NT4 Domain User Manager, Server Manager (NEXUS)</command></para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
			</para>
                </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect2>

</sect1>

</chapter>
